# **Kurt Taylor**

Last updated: Nov 2020

Address: 70 Richmond Road, Bristol BS6 5EW
Telephone Number: +447425608190
Email Address: kurt.taylor@bristol.ac.uk
Date of Birth: July 16<sup>th</sup>, 1994

## **Profile**

A motivated, adaptable individual with well-honed communication skills from a diversified set of experiences. Strong track record in science education with an in-depth understanding of epidemiology. A love for writing and exceptional organisation and management capabilities. An intense curiosity and thirst for intellectual stimulation. Experience in leading large international scientific collaborations. I am in the final year of a 4-year PhD studentship seeking opportunities and experiences that could lead to a successful career in scientific research.

#### **Education**

- 2017-2021 Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Integrative Cardiovascular Science (Epidemiology); University of Bristol, UK
  - o Thesis title: The epidemiology of congenital heart disease: identifying causal maternal risk factors.
  - o Fully funded studentship via the British Heart Foundation.
  - Year 1 is an interdisciplinary training year with years 2-4 focusing on my main PhD research.
  - I have gained experience in bioinformatic analysis, publishing in high-impact scientific journals, laboratory work, teaching, public speaking and presenting to a wide-range of audiences.
- 2014-2017 Bachelor of Science (BSc Hons), Sport and Exercise Science, First; University of Surrey, UK
  - Deep understanding of human biology, psychology and biomechanics developed through rigorous academic units as well as varied laboratory sessions

## **Employment and Experience**

My employment to date has taught me how to work effectively on my own and also as part of a team; having been employed from a young age, my worth ethic has excelled, learning to use my initiative to complete tasks required of me.

- January 2019 Visiting researcher, University of Copenhagen, Section of Epidemiology, Denmark
  - Visiting researcher for 2 weeks undertaking analyses as part of a wider project.
- **2019/ongoing Teaching,** *University of Bristol, UK* 
  - After completing the 'starting to teach' training course, I was enrolled as a teacher on the Bristol Medical School short course: Introduction to epidemiology.
- 2019/ongoing Freelance medical writer, Aspire Scientific, UK
  - As a freelance medical writer, I help produce a diverse range of high-quality scientific materials predominantly in the form of scientific manuscripts. This role often has strict deadlines.
- 2018/ongoing Club captain, Bristol and West AC, UK
  - Being the men's club captain for my running club is a rewarding task and helps me make use of my exceptional organisational skills.
- 2019 Events organisation, MRC Integrative Epidemiology Unit, UK
  - I was part of the organisation committee for the 2019 International Mendelian Randomization conference.
- May 2016-August 2016 Summer internship as a clinical exercise scientist, Surrey Human Performance Institute, UK
  - A patient-facing position located within a lab at Surrey Sports Park, as well as carrying out Cardiopulmonary Exercise Testing at Ashford and St Peter's Hospital.
- August 2013-January 2015 Sales advisor, Vodafone UK
- December 2010 August 2013 Fire protection engineer, Pipetek services Ltd and Bryland Fire Ltd.

# **Kurt Taylor**

## **Publications and research**

I am an advocate of open science and the publication of pre-specified analysis plans to improve reproducibility and prevent publication bias. A list of my active and ongoing projects can be found here: <a href="https://osf.io/82vq6/">https://osf.io/82vq6/</a>.

#### Published research

- Taylor K, McBride N, J Goulding N et al. Metabolomics datasets in the Born in Bradford cohort [version 1; peer review: awaiting peer review]. Wellcome Open Res 2020, 5:264
   (https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16341.1)
- 2. **Taylor K**, Thomas R, Mumme M *et al*. Ascertaining and classifying cases of congenital anomalies in the ALSPAC birth cohort [version 1; peer review: awaiting peer review]. *Wellcome Open Res* 2020, **5**:231 (https://doi.org/10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16339.1)
- 3. **Taylor, K**.; L. Santos Ferreira, D.; West, J.; Yang, T.; Caputo, M.; A. Lawlor, D. Differences in Pregnancy Metabolic Profiles and Their Determinants between White European and South Asian Women: Findings from the Born in Bradford Cohort. *Metabolites 9, 190* (2019). <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.3390/metabo9090190">https://dx.doi.org/10.3390/metabo9090190</a>
- 4. **Taylor, K.**, Davey Smith, G., Relton, C.L. *et al.* Prioritizing putative influential genes in cardiovascular disease susceptibility by applying tissue-specific Mendelian randomization. *Genome Med* 11, 6 (2019). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13073-019-0613-2">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13073-019-0613-2</a>

#### **Pre-prints**

- 1. **Taylor K**, Elhakeem A, Nader JLT, Yang T, Isaevska E, Richiardi L, et al. The effect of maternal pre-/early-pregnancy BMI and pregnancy smoking and alcohol on congenital heart diseases: a parental negative control study. *medRxiv*; 2020 Sep. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.09.29.20203786">https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.09.29.20203786</a>
- 2. Richardson TG, Mykkanen J, Pahkala K, Ala-Korpela M, Bell JA, **Taylor K**, et al. Evaluating the direct effects of childhood adiposity on adult systemic metabolism: A multivariable Mendelian randomization analysis. medRxiv; 2020 Aug. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.08.25.20181412
- 3. Corbin LJ, Taylor AE, White SJ, Williams CM, **Taylor K**, den Bosch MT van, et al. Epigenetic regulation of PAR4-related platelet activation: mechanistic links between environmental exposure and cardiovascular disease [Internet]. bioRxiv; 2018 Nov. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/473728">https://doi.org/10.1101/473728</a>

### Presentations, talks and public speaking

#### **Oral presentations**

- June 2020 Society for Epidemiologic Research 2020, Boston, USA
  - Invited for oral presentation (meeting cancelled due to COVID-19 pandemic) Using an untargeted metabolomics platform to explore associations between maternal metabolites and congenital heart disease in the offspring.
- 4<sup>th</sup> October 2019 University of Surrey, Surrey, UK
  - I was invited to give a one hour talk about my time at the University of Surrey and how I progressed to a successful PhD student. Audience consisted of ~50 new undergraduate students.
- 27<sup>th</sup> September 2019 Born in Bradford Science Festival, Bradford, UK
  - Sofa session lasting 1 hour 10 mins talking to a mixed audience including members of the public, researchers and policy makers about my research and what we use blood samples for in the Born in Bradford cohort.

### **Poster presentations**

- 22<sup>nd</sup> October 2019 DOHaD 2019, Melbourne, Australia
  - Poster presentation Differences in Pregnancy Metabolic Profiles and Their Determinants between
     White European and South Asian Women: Findings from the Born in Bradford Cohort.

## **Applied Qualifications, Training and Key Skills**

Where possible, I attend educational courses which could benefit my research and personal development. I am always keen on learning and have previously studied free online courses. Some examples of the training and qualifications I have received to date are listed below.

#### Bristol Medical School short training courses

- Introduction to epidemiology (5 days)
- Introduction to statistics (5 days)
- Mendelian randomisation (3 days)
- Systematic reviews and meta-analysis (4 days)
- Causal inference in epidemiology (3 days)
- Genetic epidemiology (5 days)
- Register of exercise professionals' level 3 personal trainer
- Biostatical analysis of genotype data
- Data Skills Workshop, November 2019
  - Funded by Cancer Research UK. Involved an application process to be accepted onto the course.
     Main focus on reproducible research.

### Statistical packages

- o R (proficient)
- Stata (basic use)
- Microsoft Office (proficient)

#### Public engagement of science

- o Public speaking at Born in Bradford Science Festival, September 2019
- Cancer Research UK public engagement training workshop
- Communicating my research through social media. Example: <a href="https://twitter.com/KurtSci1994/status/1174329499313475585?s=20">https://twitter.com/KurtSci1994/status/1174329499313475585?s=20</a>

#### <u>Interests</u>

I have a real passion for endurance-based sports, adventure and understanding how the body physiologically reacts to these types of activity. Since the age of eleven, I have raised thousands of pounds for various charities; my proudest achievement was successfully climbing Mount Kilimanjaro for my local hospice; a truly amazing and challenging experience. I am a competitive distance runner, training 6 or 7 days a week and competing on a national level. My running has taken me to places such as the high Atlas Mountains in Morocco and quiet suburban villages in The Gambia.